welcome back everyone this is our
third session of the applied active
inference symposium with professor
carl fristen hosted by the active
inference lab
and it's june 21st 2021
we're here representing the dot tools
organizational unit of the lab
the third organizational unit in the lab
and the goals
of dot tools is to enable
effective tool and instrument use for
all active inference
lab processes so that's just using the
digital tools affordances that we have
better as well as exploring and
designing
affordances for our niche modifying our
niche
resulting in effective action as well as
innovations in tool development
as with the other groups we've been
meeting weekly in tools
and having a lot of awesome insights
related to where
active inference might come into play
and that's what we're excited to talk to
you about
some of the core insights from the work
in this unit
relates to learning by doing the
recognition that modern
systems are cyber physical everything is
really
intercalated with the digital and also
we found it really
refreshing kind of like a two-stroke
engine to be
sidestepping or complementing or
augmenting
some of these philosophical discussions
with technical clarifications
and two ways in which we've seen that
play out on the left here
is a quote from you during a 2019
dropbox blog post when you wrote that
technology is the natural extension
of active inference beyond the single
person which of course brings technology
far from brings being something
artificial into the realm of extended
and embedded
cognition in our niche and then on the
right side
is a slide from a very recent talk by
bert devry
on beyond deep learning natural ai
systems
speaking to several applications in
hardware and software
of active inference for example gesture
recognition
robotic navigation and also audiometry
for
hearing aids and one effort that
we're starting up now is a
net hack challenge it's kind of a video
game
played in text characters and we're
assembling a team with already multiple
interested participants
to get an active inference agent on the
playing field so to speak
and have people maybe update their
generative model when they see that it
doesn't have to be a three billion
parameter
neural network trained for six months on
the gpu
but what if it's enough to just be
curious and to want to succeed
those are the kinds of things that
motivate us in dot tools
so we can start right off the bat with
asking
how can we use active inference to
structure the process
of innovation and tool development and
how can active inference concepts
help us design for complex agents that
are interacting in complex niches
for example thinking about niche
modification extension of affordances
reduction of uncertainty or structuring
of communications
again great questions um
so the use fact of inference to
structure the process of innovation and
tool development um
that is um in itself
um an entertaining notion
um
in the sense that um you are a
realization of
active inference and you know i'm
mindful that
um your your nice use of um
the combination of of you know well
the emphasis on curiosity um
as the imperative that
drives most of our behavior is exactly
the imperative that as a scientist
drives me and most of the people i know
um and in a sense i would imagine
also drives your initiative and your
laboratory
so all the questions you are asking are
really you know
how how do i make the next move in order
to
resolve uncertainty about uh
about about your particular um
model of how say artificial intelligence
or human communication is going to
is going to evolve um so
yeah in that light i think there are two
levels to the answer
the first one is just to celebrate and
um
you know um acknowledge that you are
engaging in the scientific process as
formulated by
active inference that you are on a
journey of
trying to satisfy curiosity that will be
never ending
um and that speaks to your one of your
themes in the previous slide about
learning is doing
the only way you're going to um resolve
or say that curiosity is to go out there
and see what happens
and that is um that that is exactly the
right thing to do
a more practical level answer though i
think speaks to the tool development
because one of the um one of the
fundaments
of of active inference is the
appreciation
that if you just want to maximize
the likelihood that this uh your kind
of um world model or generative model
that entails the way that you exchange
with and interrogate
and ping a world is the right world
um that is articulated out there in
terms of the sense of extended
cognition for example in terms of the
the software tools or the your
educational tools that you're
you're making available then all of this
is still subject
to the imperative to minimize complexity
so in maximizing the likelihood that
these tools will be out there and
in a sense you're saying this model
this way of narrating
uh the way that the world works you
provide an accurate description that is
as simple as possible
so there's a you know you cannot escape
the complexity i'm speaking like you're
going to schmidt over now which is
a good thing in this instance um
so that means you've got to find the
simplest tools and it's interesting that
you
um you you um highlighted visa's
contribution because you know
again just practically thinking what's
the game here the game here
is to write down the or
find the best hypothesis the best
explanation for my lived world
and my me could be active inference labs
and the lived world is everything that
you have to engage with in terms of
educational commercial or academic
partners um
so you've got to write down you've got
to um
explore the model space in terms to find
the right
model generative model of the way that
your
your system or your organization
works um that um
the first steps in writing down the
generative model are basically to
um define its structure in terms of the
sort of hidden factors or latent factors
and their interactions and all that good
stuff
um but it has to be done in the simplest
way possible
um so what's the simplest way of writing
down
a a generative model while it's to write
down a
bayesian um um graphical
model what does that mean
for the actual coding practically
and the software schemes and
implementation that you would either
offer to people or pre-package in terms
of
user interfaces then it's going to be
message passing on those graphs
um and that and i'm trying to get back
to bert davis's um
factor lab a foreign lab formation
so to my mind that's the simplest most
generic
bit of computer science that you would
come across
in the service of finding the right
software tools
to build absolutely everything because
absolutely everything
can be written down as a generative
model if there's a generative model
there
it's a bayesian dependency graph if
there's a bayesian pentagraph you know
there's a factor graph
if it's a factor graph then you know
there's a message passing scheme
what is that message passing scheme it's
just a free energy variation free energy
minimizing message passing scheme so
um i would i would imagine that as tool
development
increases that there will be a move
towards a common language that will look
very much like
um bert's um phony style
message passing and within that um
you know you've got very limited choices
um
which is a good thing because that again
speaks to this minimization of
complexity and just
course graining the world and your world
um at its courses level that will
sustain
an accurate account or a precise account
of what you want to
want to achieve um so i'm thinking here
the tools just have to come in two
flavors they have to deal with
continuous state space um generative
models
to interface with you know of the kind
you need for robotics
um but also uh the other flavor will be
in discrete state space and
your latent states um latent um discrete
late states
uh models uh that you need to do say
computational linguistics
or you know modeling
the climate in in various states um
and we know that the um
we know all the message passing schemes
that would
be entailed by a commitment to one of
those two kinds of models
um in the sense of generalized bayesian
filtering for the continuous state space
um and by generalized ui
generalized courts and motion uh which
generalize things like kalman filtering
um and on the discrete state space side
you're talking about either belief
propagation or variational message
passing
so when you just think about it what you
have to do in providing
tools of a software kind or a simulation
kind um you know happily there aren't
many choices you have to worry about
um so you know you know in that sense um
all you need to do is to make sure that
your tools accommodate both
generalized bayesian filtering and
bleed propagation and or variational
message passing and then you're using
off-the-shelf
technology which brings us back to well
what's the real problem then well the
real problem is writing down the charity
model
what sort of problems how would you
unpack those problems in terms of
innovation and tool development
well it's solving the model selection
problem um so sometimes i think
you sort of when describing the the the
space of problems that
are faced say with um generalized ai or
aji um you know
you you can unpack them at different
different
spatial temporal scales into the
inference problem
into the learning problem and into the
selection problem
by which i mean using bayesian model
selection to get the right structure
you know do i use six or twelve layers
in my deep neural network
do i use a convolutional model or do you
use a transformer
these are basically problems of um that
are solved
if you have a mechanics that can score
the structure
enabling you to select the right form so
that i think is going to be
um a focus of innovation in the
um yeah it already is but certainly in
the in the near future in terms of
development
and in the sense that i think the
inference and learning problems they're
solved problems that you can just go to
burton
and get your favorite uh message passing
scheme or you can
uh keep at the level of your educational
or academic
um message passing user matlab schemes
that
we generate you know here here in london
for toy problems
and what is not i think um a sole
problem
and will require an innovative solution
is the structural learning problem or
the selection problem
now exploring not the right hypothesis
but
you know we're in the principled way
um exploring the space of generative
models you might want to bring to
the table um and that you know that
um that has many many different issues
and you know
things that come to mind are of course
that you could do it
in um in a bottom-up way by trying out
new hypotheses where you get those from
you get them from experts in the field
because effectively they are
bootstrapping themselves
on the basis of our prior beliefs or
your knowledge about how how something
works
you can do it in a top-down approach by
having over-parameterized but um
over-expressive models but with very
weak imprecise parameterizations and
then use basic model reduction
to solve the selection problem these are
ways that people are thinking at the
moment
but this thinking is innovative
innovative because i don't think there
are any
any clear answers so um
how would you use active inference to
solve the uh structure learning problem
well in a sense um it's already being
used in the sense of basic model
selection as natural selection
but you really want to speed that up and
make it work within your
within your commercial academic
lifetimes but i would imagine that
exactly the same principles
would be brought to me there and you
know
that almost answers the next one how can
active imprints concepts how to design
complex agents interacting in complex
niches you just have to build these
things as
as a proof of principle and hypothesis
testing
and the nice thing is you know all the
um
the machinery and the tools that would
be requisite
in building these things right from the
variational message passing using say
forney lab through to now you've got the
right
fitness function when it comes to using
say a genetic algorithm to explore a
structured space
and what is that fitness function it's
it's it's the
you know the evidence low bound or the
variational free energy
um so you've got all the maths in place
this is a question
that i think of of of simulating these
things and providing proof of principle
how you would translate that into the
real world i i i
i don't know at this stage i'm afraid
i think you know a challenging first
step would be
um you know to to actually use uh
robotics
uh or in silico or you know sort of
hardware or possibly
you know a lot of excitement at the
moment using soft uh soft robotics
and actually um you know in you you
design
your niche and and um see what happens
and then turn your attention to niche
construction
where you now acknowledge that the niche
itself is also
succumbing to the principles not of
active inference enough
in and of itself um in the sense that
niches don't plan
um but certainly um in the
fep sort of um vanilla
um free energy minimizing approach um
so yeah i haven't actually thought about
that before that but that's a you know
an interesting asymmetry when it comes
to simulating multi-agent interactions
uh in the context of niche construction
where
often it is the case that the the niche
is just the other agents in an ensemble
um but if you now actually include
the the environment as part of the niche
that is playing host to all the denizens
that are the ensemble of
uh active infants agents um
then i there is this distinction between
um the um the ability to
to plan the consequences of action um
that would entail optimization the
expected free energy
versus simply reflexively minimizing
surprisal
by um um by minimizing uh free energy
as an evidence bound um and put that
more simply more intuitively and you're
either with generative models that
support planning or not
you know so there's nothing i think
fundamentally different between these
approaches it's just if you've got a
generative model
that is a model of the paths into the
future
consequent upon what you how you act
upon the world
that's a much richer deeper genetic
model than the kinds of genetic models
that would be
applicable for a thermostat or an
environment um
and it's likely that the environment
that
you know i have in mind here which is um
you know
a warehouse that you've got a sentient
robot going around trying to collect the
right things so the robot can plan
but the environment the niche can't it
will still conform to the principles the
very
you know the free energy principle there
will still be particles and
things that are conserved and they will
still fall and behave in a predictable
way that may
even be a thermostat controlling the
temperature but none of these things are
planning
so there's a there's an interesting
asymmetry that gets into the game when
you're talking about
complex agents interacting in complex
niches
part of that complexity has to be a
specification of whether
the complexity entails planning or not
and it just creates different problem
spaces certainly in the context of
multi-agent
simulations so that's that's how i would
um
sort of carve up the the problem spaces
you know in terms of implicitly um
problem spaces that will only be
explored by
doing and by doing i just mean actually
realizing physically these processes
in the kind of situations that you think
are going to be useful for
for the future thanks for the answer and
it's really
fascinating about using simulation
so that selection can happen within the
generation of for example a startup
rather than between generations because
of course we can let organisms or
startups proliferate and then let
pruning occur at the generational scale
or
there could be ways to design so that
that selection occurs within a
generation
more like learning and development
rather than intergenerational selection
so awesome points there
this could be a broad question but we're
curious
what areas of applied active inference
you think just might be exciting
promising or important
so my my personal usual response to this
um comes in um in two flavors
the first is from the point of view of a
theoretical biologist um and a
psychiatrist
so if you know if you can understand
how a a normal sentient artifact or
person behaves
then that creates a space in which you
can think about
false inference and false learning um or
certainly some optional from the point
of view of
um minimizing surprise or or free energy
so that's a fancy way of saying
understanding the computational basis of
psychopathology
so the you know there's a whole
literature on using active imprints
as a if you like a normative
framework within which to um
provide an ontology of false
inference or failures or aberrant active
inference
um and why would you want to do that
well
if it can all be reduced just to the
good belief updating and the good
message passing
we actually have a very um quite a
comprehensive understanding of neuronal
message passing and all its physiology
and all the
um the roles of various
neurotransmitters and
you know microcircuits and uranus made
that underwrite that kind of neuronal
message passing
and implicitly we also then have a
fairly um a fairly fine-grained
understanding of
um the role of neurotransmitters and the
pharma
of the consequences of pharmacological
interventions
in the context of uh experience
dependent learning and
an influence of the kind we've been
talking about so from a
translational perspective um literally
translating
um the formalism on offer from active
inference
into the clinical domain that would be
one you know
one motivation for the for developing
this theoretical framework
the other one is more you know
more in the line of technology and
artificial general intelligence so then
the question is well
i now want to build sentient artifacts
and not only build them but
build brothers and sisters so they are
complex and interact and learn to love
each other
in a complex environment that could
include me um
and you know then you've got you've got
um a a clear offer from active inference
as to the design principles you might
want to use
to to actually um build these artifacts
and then they're interesting questions
about what the
what kind of art artifact do you want to
build
um and we've already discussed the
difference between a thermostat
and a uh a sentient robot going around
collecting your um your next sort of um
home delivery
um there are different kinds of genitive
models so now you ask the question okay
what are the promise the exciting and
promising
kinds of artifacts uh
as defined by their genitive models um
that one might expect to see in the
future
and then we get into the world of um you
know
genetic model support planning so we're
talking about deep charity models where
they have a temporal depth
what are the next stages that you might
be looking at well there's a
also a sort of hierarchical depth um
that would at some point um
first of all include the capacity to
deploy precision um and why is that
important well as soon as you have
um the deploying the precision
as a process of inference you are now
um you have now a normative theory for
this kind of mental action or covert
action
so one example of this would be i don't
know how the
the technology but i can almost
i can be assured that i know i know um
what it's trying to do but thinking
about transformer networks and
um the way that attention selection
operates in this in this context
what you're saying is you can actually
optimize the attention selection
as an inference process using active
inference or an evidence lower bound
and where you're now predicting
what things to attend to and what and
what does you know what particular
ways to switch on which which ways to
switch off um
and at that point you can understand
that as mental action
so when when the transformers or
variation auto encoders
start to now optimize
their estimates of the posterior
precision at lower layers in an auto
encoder
it's now acquired the capacity for
mental action
and it now will pay attention to various
representations and possibly even
various data sources that's not magical
we do that every day in the sort of mdp
and you know and use it to explain a lot
of
the attentional mechanisms implemented
in in the brain
if you can migrate that technology into
deep learning
you would have taken one baby step
towards true sentience which is mental
action
the next uh step would be um okay
so um how can i now minimize the
complexity
of my genitive model where my genitive
model now actually
includes this meta inference in the
sense i am now
providing predictions about my inference
because i'm controlling the precision of
hierarchically subordinate message
passing
and at that point you start to think
well perhaps
one simplifying um one way
of simplifying uh the computational
complexity of the you know the
complexity part of the
um the generative the the inference
um would be to carve up
different states of attentional
deployment in exactly the same way we're
talking about carving up people into
biden versus trump voters you know a
simple
stable uh complexity minimizing carving
up
which suddenly suggests to you that you
can now equip
an artifact with states of mind
so that they can be in four states of
mind they can be happy they can be sad
they can be confident they can be unsure
and they will have to infer given all
the evidence at hand
including the message passing lower in
the hierarchy what state of mind it is
in
and if you now include in terms of the
sensory evidence
you know the voltage on their batteries
or
you know some measurement of their
interception you now have something
that's going very very close
to say ryan's um notion of
um of emotions so now you've got um
a part of the genitive model is now
inferring
what state of mind am i in as the best
explanation for all these
interceptive um embodied sensations
not just the proprioceptive you know
state of my actuators
but also um you know are they getting a
bit sticky
um uh you know um are they
is there some wear and tear you know all
my batteries charge
all of these things come together um as
part evidence in conjunction with all
the usual visual
laid out auditory um uh sort of sorry
acoustic
inputs um to to actually
um supply evidence for a posterior
belief i'm in this state of mind
i'm anxious my battery's running out
this immediately
creates different prior preferences cost
functions if you like
that would be applied to your policies
because you've got a deep changing model
that
plans into the future so now you've got
an artifact that not only has the
capacity for mental action
it's now got the capacity to be in
different emotional states
the next step is to say hang on so there
are these different states can i now
equip it with the mineral selfhood
can the hypothesis that i am actually an
artifact
provide empirical priors that reduce the
complexity
of my message passing at subordinate
levels that is generating
um that is inferring the state of mind
that i am i'm in
that in turn um um um
you know optimizes the uh posteriors of
the precisions of various likelihood
mappings or
or preferences over policies so at this
point you're starting to get
to artifacts that could have minimal
self-awareness
the next stage would be that's only
going to be ever
um that's only going to be i think
useful um
when it when you consider dialectic
interactions again because the only
rationale
for having self-awareness is to
disambiguate
um um
self from other which means that there
must be some confusion
in um or some uncertainty
um at hand in order to justify the
resolution uncertainty justify that
complexity of the model
um which means that you um have to be
interacting with or exchanging with
things that are sufficiently like you to
license
the inclusion in your genitive moral
of a self versus other or that you
are like me or not like me so we
actually come down back
full circle to what we're talking about
before in terms of inferring who i
am i talking to so this i think this you
know
structurally something quite fundamental
about this
inference problem are you a creature
like me or not or
are are you like one of those are you a
pet are you a plant
um you know just being able to carve up
this
world in a way that is self-referential
necessarily entails a minimal selfhood
in the inferences of these
that speaks to the importance of getting
the
the necessary evidence from the
environment that would
um be if you like license that degree of
complexity and the only kinds of
environments that can supply
that degree the license that degree of
complexity
are when that environment that econish
is actually
is actually comprises other agents
like me that make it if you like
worthwhile me inferring oh it's me not
you doing that
so i would imagine then the most
promising
applications um of active influence in
constructing sentient artifacts pets and
you know carers or or convert
people things that you can converse with
and would be to grow them
certainly with themselves but
more importantly with you there so they
can learn by they're doing with
you there so they they want to they're
curious about you
and you're curious about them at that
point
one could argue that's the only scenario
which you're going to have any
empathetic interaction um you know you
know
with these artifacts so i'm sure there
are other applications in terms of
um climate change or commerce or
whatever but
in terms of imagining what you could
produce
you could sell i would i would imagine
that
you know a mindful robot that actually
is curious genuinely curious
about you because that will teach you
something about itself
thanks for that answer um the idea of
tools for attention
and of design and engineering for
regimes of attention
to use an active inference term is
really essential
and what you were talking about there
with the phone first off
before the internet when there weren't
other devices of similar kind there was
no need to communicate
out and what we've seen is that as
there's more and more devices of
similar or interoperable kinds new
levels of organization have to emerge
and then i thought about the anxiety
that a person might feel
when their phone is running low on
battery
right now that sensor reading is getting
emotionally offloaded to the human so
we could have that anxiety on device
so let's have a more relaxing
relationship with our phone and then as
you pointed out
it would be the um incipient steps of
selfhood
or perhaps what they could even call a
cell phone if i'm allowed one pun per
symposium
the next question is what kinds of tools
have been most helpful in your work in
research
which includes many areas such as spm
and
dcm that a lot of people who are just
learning about active inference might
not be very familiar with
and what kinds of tools don't exist yet
but might be helpful for active
inference work
um so the mathematical tools so you know
and i'm often asked this question uh of
students you know do i need to be able
to do maths to
to contribute to this field um and
if so what kind of maths um um
i won't tell you what my answer is but
what i have found useful is certainly
mathematics
but not not necessarily very high end
this is always
wikipedia level mathematics and in
particular
um dynamical systems theory information
theory and linear algebra are probably
all you need to
to to to do everything really um and
indeed you could read most of quantum
electrodynamics as basically linear
algebra
with a bit of probability theory
underneath it
so that that has been the mainstay that
that is
you know you know if there is one
tool that it would be the tool and the
language um
of maths and relatively simple maths and
the second thing is to um the learning
is doing
um you know a c1 do one teach one
um um ethos i think applies
very pragmatically in this context um
which means it
you know it's actually um very useful if
you can get students to actually
build their own little um simulated
artifacts
um and even more useful when you know
when they can actually code it out
themselves
which means you need access to a high
level at least third generation
programming language
um that you know a student can get um
fluent with
should they want to not only to use
the existing tools but you know try and
write it down themselves without having
to spend years
training as a computer scientist so i
found matlab
very useful in that respect not because
it's terribly efficient although i have
to say actually some of the
matrix operators and under the hood
tensor operators are
actually much more efficient than people
give them credit for um because it
actually came from
x-ray crystallography however what's
really useful about it is it uses the
same
syntax that you would find in a book on
linear algebra
which didactically or education is
really quite important
when it comes to writing and reading the
code
so we have deliberately stuck with
matlab not because it's computationally
efficient
or that it's open source um it should be
i don't think it is
um but simply because it's it's
configured in a way that
that people reading um standard texts
one-on-one texts and
in the new algebra and the like would be
able to see how it transcribes into a
computer language
so that's been a really useful uh um a
really useful tool
and looking ahead um i imagine that
you know you one's gonna need open
access and possibly more
i i um i don't know could go out the way
i'm just thinking about first of all
people like bert and forney lab in terms
of
very generic very high-end
specifications
of message passing in computer science
um that may be that that's the level you
want people to actually compose their
genitive models and their their
artifacts and
they don't even need to know about
linear algebra and even less information
theory
what they need to know is that the
language of relational
you know the object relations and and
how to specify
just different classes of exponential
probability distributions and you know
is it categorical is it continuous is it
always positive or
it can be positive and negative and that
may be quite sufficient to write down
a factor graph or a generative model and
then everything else is just off the
shelf a little right itself
um so that would certainly be um
possibly helpful in the future and so
i'm moving on to what kinds of tools
don't exist at the moment so i'm
thinking of it
what i never used it but i would i
imagine would be
bert's forney lab facilities
but uh offered as um an application or a
user interface
that allowed you to compose genitive
models
and then just hit compose a genetic
model compose
a genetic process the actual world
that's going to be modeled
and then there's click run and see what
happens that you know that would that
would be that would be really useful i
think
um having said that the other side to to
to
future scoping here is i repeat this
sort of um
leveraging um more specialized or other
fields
uh and the you know um amortizing
certain
parts of of inference or learning to
infer
um or indeed inferring to learn
or learning to plan or learning to infer
how you plan
so or starting to sort of see what parts
of the inference
process are so conserved that they could
actually be amortized and learned
and certainly that looks as how that's
what the brain
has done for example there are people
who think that the cerebellum
has basically learned how the motor
cortex
does its online kl control or um
carbon filtering and therefore um
lens of fluency and a computational
efficiency
to the message passing which um you know
we which in its absence um it doesn't
mean you can't do something
it just means you can't do it as
fluently and as gracefully as quickly as
you
your as you know as you could with a
cerebellum indeed when you
um have a cerebellar lesion all that
really happens is you become a bit
clumsy
um and slow um um so
um that those kinds of tools
your a quick and cheerful integration or
importing um various amortization
and deep learning technology um into
a um a forney style message passing
scheme that could
support any kind of genitive model i
think would
we you know would be really really
useful
awesome thank you approaching this
nexus from another angle
what kinds of tools and platforms could
inform
transdisciplinary highly contextual
and engaged teams that are working with
these approaches
active lab we hope to be working with
others to be
developing the active inference
curriculum
and body of knowledge more broadly but
when teams are actually
using these kinds of approaches what
kinds of platforms
might exist to enable their work
um yeah okay i have a strong suspicion
that you know the answer to this
so i'm trying to guess at the answer
that you you know is the right answer
and i'm not doing very well here
um so um i
you know i think that you you you that
we've already talked and
and certainly implicitly in the way that
you presented the ambitions
uh and implicitly send the questions and
you know
all the answers are there whether that's
trying to engage through
education whether it's trying to engage
through insight
um using say you know embodied
experience
illustrations of the basic principles
whether it's
supplying um games or user interfaces
graphical user interfaces to facilitate
the designing and enacting and the
playing with um gender models and
an active inference i think these are
all um
uh your obvious and laudable ways
of um of you know
of leveraging um what what what what
what um active inference has to ha
has to offer um participatory
yeah that's um i mean the the learning
is doing thing and the c1 teach one do
one
you know keeps coming back to mind um
and the course
completely licenses the participatory
aspect
um but what kind of participation did
you have in mind are you talking about
sort of hackathons are you talking about
sort of
um playing games with active inference
computers that start to start to
hate you or love you or what what level
of participation were you
yeah stephen do you want to give a quick
thought on a few kinds of participation
or what does that mean to you
yeah one area is quite interesting is in
psycho drama
they use action methods like action
sociometry or spatial
activities to look at how people relate
to their experience
in a dynamic way so physically so i've
been looking at ways that
spatial participatory approaches can
unpack people's relationships to
different niches or different workplaces
or different types of embodied
experience
and then that could be visible
to be put into active influence type
geometries i see
okay right right well there's a great
example so
um so two things um that i've come
across before
are the um architectural design
um and the um the importance
of um
not just uh sort of pragmatically afford
and says you know can i walk up but i
can i sit there but also the epistemic
affordance is
you know if i look over there um what
would i learn about the space around me
if i go around that corner
so um there is um you know
embryonic interest um in in you know
in my world um from um
the architectural sciences and you know
and architecture
in and of itself that um is is
could in principle be motivated it's not
discipline
because it's half like art and half-life
science but
certainly some of their ideas are very
much um
aligned with certain gibsonian notions
of performance and
also um the um the affordances the dual
aspect performance is brought by
expected free energy under active
inference so it's not just
you know am i the kind of creature that
can sit on this on this particular chair
but also what will i learn if i'd if i
so do
and so things become epistemically
attractive to engage with
the other domain um is um
in entertainment and in music and in
particular um
the joy of synchronization and mutual
predictability are minimizing free
energy through mutual prediction
uh prediction when singing or dancing
together
or indeed um interacting with a slightly
greater
asymmetry in terms of being a member of
an audience
um watching a band for example so
um you know one of the key things that
comes out of that kind of research is
ways
of measuring the implicit
generalized synchrony that you get from
having
this information geometry that i was
talking about before
that rests upon there being um
a synchronization manifold between the
inside and the outside
but if the outside is another inside
from another person's point of view
what you now have is something called a
synchronization manifold
so there's a mathematical image or
space um to actually talk about
mutual inference and mutual active
influence and engagement and
communication
singing together for example or die
chronically exchanging
messages that does actually
translate mathematically into movement
and belief
updating on a synchronization manifold
and that has
real world correlates you can measure
that using um
kinematic you're putting leds on people
who are dancing together for example
or measuring heart rate variability or
galvanic skin responses or
doing eye tracking or indeed eeg and
start to
so there's quite a lot of work in um
[Music]
in things like hyper scanning and
in um you know sort of ethology
and dance
disciplines um where
in the arts in the life sciences where
they do
use a lot of these techniques to
quantify the degree of generalized
synchrony what it would be
nice to do is actually try and model
that synchrony or understand that
synchrony in terms of
um movement on the synchronization
manifold which is sort of the mutual
uh belief updating and one thing which
comes out of that just in discussion if
not if no
if no further is the reciprocal
the circular causality that is necessary
um
to maintain um that generalized
synchrony um the particular
synchronization manifold we're talking
about for
from the point of view of active
imprints of course is mediated across
the markov blanket as of the active and
sensory states
and but in general the
[Music]
um you need to have reciprocal coupling
um
in in order to to get to get
synchronization so directed coupling
doesn't work
um and if that's true what that means is
that
engaging as an audience for example or
participating as a spectator
will only really work in terms of
establishing that generalized synchrony
that you are
chasing and while you're chasing it well
as soon as you have a generalized
symphony you've got predictability for
for free for all and that's a good thing
because that minimizes free energy
you know more predictable you can make
the world the better the better it is
um from the point of view of free energy
um
but you can only do that if as a member
of the audience
or a witness to something you can
actually actively intervene on it
so that brings to mind how could you get
for example
discussion discussions with um friends
of of maxwell
yeah if you wanted to promote virtual
concerts on you know online for example
during the pandemic what you don't have
online which is what glues things
together things like mosh pits in in
sort of carnivals and
festivals um is you don't have
the audience participation the the
applaud the wars the you know the
um the lighter waving or the light
waving um
so how would you get that back into into
a virtual
um virtual experience because that would
be absolutely essential
you know i think to actually engage
people otherwise you know you
you'll be you you'll be just a pop
concert on television
so you know more than just if you like
um
revealing the underlying correlates of
that generalized synchrony in terms of
the
eeg traces of the the dancers
or doing some sensory mapping from
um the their motion to auditory import
you know
just making it making the sensory
evidence that supports
the mutual inference um more precise and
more available
just by having it displayed say by
putting
putting motion in sound or sound in
motion um
or eeg electrocathographic measures of
performance or the audience
um visualizing that and that has been
done by people like paul bushur
in barcelona more than that to actually
um enable the audience to change what
the performers are doing
you have to make you know or perhaps
what other members of the audience are
doing
so you have to empower them to close
that
um that circular causality to get that
dynamical coupling place so you get
you get the right kind of generalized
synchrony so that
um you know that that sort of
um dynamical systems perspective on
synchronization free energy minimization
certainly speaks to a particular kind of
participation and engagement
that does indeed rest upon
action-oriented approaches
but crucially it's the action of the
audience
on the performers not the performers
action on the audience uh that is is is
usually
what you need to pay more pay more
attention i don't know if that was that
the kind of thing you were you were
thinking about yeah that's really a
useful answer actually
yeah we were thinking about that and and
some participatory immersive
theater type events and other
participation in
collective meaning making so that's the
type of thing that we're looking at
and it reminds me of the live stream
affordance which is relatively
novel but allows people to be asking
questions and it enables not just
efficient production
of material in a one-shot approach but
it allows the feedback and i can't help
but add that it's that
affordance for participation for example
speak now or forever hold your peace
that expands the wedding into the
community
because there is the opportunity for
feedback it's not just a breakaway click
it's actually something that remains
integrated through the affordance for
participation
so i'll turn to the last question for
this
section how might future modeling
involve large-scale patterns in social
data sets
and working backwards to infer their
hidden causes
for example in the case of pandemic
modeling governance
economic other situations
[Music]
well this is a very practical and very
prestigious question because of course a
lot of people are asking themselves that
now
specifically with respect to pandemic
morals but also
the people who are exercised and um
have the interventional clout
um when it comes to covert are generally
also the people who are invested in
climate change problems as well so
there's a lot of um there's a lot of
noise out there at the moment about
um you know how we can harness
the um data assimilation and modeling
advances made during um the
during covert 19 and keep the momentum
up to tackle climate change
and what you know not just climate but
the economic structures that
um and financial structures and
informational um structures that are
deeply interwoven in terms of um and
climate change
and my answer is going to be somewhat
deflationary
um um and i've had this kind of
conversation before again with um
um with maxwell and and john clipping
and
kim jones and related friends and um due
actually to have another conversation
with him on
um certainly open um
open world or open cameraman um
um in the near future um
there's a temptation to take all the
high church of the free energy principle
and active influence and epistemic
foraging and
all of that good stuff we were just
talking about and say oh well now let's
make it work
in terms of understanding um say the
pandemic
and you don't need to do that all you
need to do is to apply
the good scientific principles that
things like active infants appeal to
to the problem at hand and it all comes
back to the generative model
so you know all you're saying here is
how might future modelling involve
large-scale patterns of social data
um to infer the the um hidden causes
is just a statement of we need the right
generative models to make
proper sense of the big data at hand
and in saying the right charity models
we need the equipment
both to invert those models in the sense
of
inferring the parameters interactions
using the simple tools we've just talked
about they will just be
lifting it from the laboratory or um
you know continuing to you to use matlab
um but the bigger problem is what we
talked about which is the selection of
the structure learning problem
so this goes beyond just um higher
you know how many layers do i have in my
deep network much
more important i think it's a
factorization
it's knowing how many conditionally
independent factors do i need
to minimize the complexity to get the
right granularity
the right way of carving up um the
latent causes behind
all the data that is available to me
so i think the pandemic modeling is a
beautiful example of this
um because you know
the factors that determine whether
i infect you can certainly be written
down in terms of virology and the
ace receptors h2 receptors and
and basically production numbers and
transmission strengths and transmission
risks
and you know the spike proteins
but that's only half the story the other
half of the story is how likely are you
to be at work or at home when i'm at
work
are you likely to be wearing a face mask
are you going to are we going to be one
or two meters apart
so all these behavioral aspects start to
become really
important factors and even beyond that
when it comes to making sense of the
model the likelihood part of the model
that actually generates the data it can
become extremely difficult
to optimize when you start to think
about
what kind of data is at hand for example
just notification rates of
um of new cases per day
in the um of of coronavirus
now you might think oh that's that's
really great data it's
really difficult data to handle because
the different kinds of tests not only
have differential
um false positive and false negative
rates but the different ways in which
they are deployed
um really compounds that in terms of the
selection bias
so are you testing people who are
symptomatic what's the probability of
being affected if you're symptomatic
are you not are you doing survey testing
are you doing the same
amount of testing uh this week as you
were doing last week
all of these what would be if you like
from an epidemiological or a behavioral
science perspective
really under interesting factors
suddenly
now become the most important factors in
making sense of those data
but you only know that when you start to
do the uh the model comparison of the
structure learning when you actually
commit to writing down the congenital
models
and that's certainly what i've learned
um over the past
year uh now coming up for a year and a
half
um you know you know the future of
modeling is is
is um first of all it's obvious what the
future is it's just basically writing
down the right kind of um
dynamical um state-space models that
account for data
but the future is really dealing with
the problems of structural learning
and and model selection for any data
um but in particular from the big data
at hand in terms of pandemics or
um trafficking uh on on the web um
you know or climate change um so
it's a really exciting opportunity why
do people want to do it
well once you've got the the most
evidenced i.e the you know the minimum
free energy
um um
model at hand and you've got posteriors
over
all the model parameters and all the
right interactions
then you can do all sorts of stuff in
terms of
um reducing people's uncertainty about
the future
because you've quantified the
uncertainty and explained to them things
that were once uncertain about and what
isn't uncertain about
that has enormous implications for
mental health and well-being
and uh possibly even um feeding back
into finance because you always hear
well
the biggest determinant in terms of the
markets is the market confidence
it's all about the uncertainty so if you
can do uncertainty quantification
in a principled way using um
using um this kind of modeling uh
you've you've done a big thing already
but then you come to
um monitoring putative interventions
you've now got
a direct um handle posterior estimate on
the latent states you actually want to
make decisions on
so it's not the notification rates or
the number of new cases
in california today it's a number of new
people that have become infected today
and that's a very difficult thing to
infer given all of these
complicated aspects of the of the
generative model and then of course once
you
once you've established the validity of
this model um
in terms of its construct and
predictability then you can intervene on
it then you can say well what would
happen if i changed this or what
happened if i changed that
um and what would happen now what would
happen in the future
so that you know you're suddenly in a
world of quantitative modelling
um where
you can start to ask some very powerful
questions and also
share with everybody who matters
and the products of your inference so
you can now start to think about
having supplementing the weather
forecast with a
uh an epidemic forecast you know the
virus in your area
and tomorrow we expect you know you can
also do that the markets
and these kinds of things i think are
going to be more important
um when people um or when the current
generation
get to your generation i guess
um start to wrestle more with climate
change
because they're going to want to not
just know what whether it's going to
rain tomorrow they're going to want to
know
you know at the level not just the
weather but the climate what are the
indicators because those indicators
um really contextualize and inform their
generative models about their place in
the world
and that global that global scale but to
provide that kind
of weather forecasting that meteorology
beyond the weather um you're going to
need to have these
these state space models probably
optimized and
you know you know in a first principle
way in relation to their their marginal
likelihood on their
or their um the the
their evidence evidence bounds um and
we've just read governance here because
governance is just positive decision
making based upon counterfactual
outcomes so
that is always underwritten by um these
these bayesian beliefs but you can't get
the basic beliefs unless you've got a
genetic model
and perhaps the consequences of action
in the future
uh there would be also interventions
either politically or financially or
um or otherwise
thank you so much again for joining this
symposium
it was really a special moment for the
lab
and we look forward to continued
interaction
so much appreciated and
we will see you all soon thanks for
everyone who's watching and we hope that
you participate
in acton flap so thanks everyone
bye